Guide to the James L. Vizzard Papers, 1942-1983
Department of Special Collections
James L. Vizzard Papers,
1942-1983
Special Collections M0324
Vizzard, James L.
16.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Gift of Father James L. Vizzard, November 4, 1980
ABSTRACT
Correspondence, reports, legislative testimony, speeches, articles, minutes, agendas, newsclippings, oral history tape and transcript, and photographs, documenting Vizzard's career as a lobbyist and worker on behalf of rural poor, migrants and braceros.
BIOGRAPHY
Father James L. Vizzard was born in San Francisco on February 17, 1916, to James L. and Mary Flaherty Vizzard. He attended Star of the Sea Grammar School and St. Ignatius High School in San Francisco. After graduating from high school, Vizzard joined the Society of Jesus in Los Gatos, California, on August 14, 1933. He received a B.A. (1939) and M.A. (1940) in philosophy from Gonzaga University in Spokane, Washington. In the early 1940s, while continuing his studies for the priesthood at Alma College in Los Gatos, Vizzard taught English and Latin at he University of Santa Clara and at Loyola High School in Los Angeles. He was ordained on June 13, 1946, by Archbishop John J. Mitty at St. Mary's Cathedral in San Francisco. In 1947, Vizzard received the degree Licentiate of Sacred Theology from Alma College. He taught at Santa Clara one more year before going east to pursue doctoral studies. Vizzard's concern for the plight of migrant farm workers in Santa Clara orchards led him to study agricultural economics. He spent three months in Europe examining farming conditions and methods. He studied at Georgetown University, the United States Department of Agriculture Graduate School, and the University of Chicago from 1949 to 1953, but frequent bouts of ill health, including repeated hospitalization for a severe back injury, prevented him form completing his doctoral studies. He returned to the University of Santa Clara, teaching there from 1953 to 1955. Seeking a way to utilize his training in agricultural economics, Vizzard accepted a post as the first Washington, D.C. legislative representative of the National Catholic Rural Life Conference (NCRLC). The NCRLC, a coalition of bishops, priests and lay people founded in 1942, sought to make the public aware of the value of rural life and to provide a forum for the discussion of farm problems. The NCRLC's educational programs, publications, lobbying and policy-making efforts were directed towards improving the spiritual and material quality of life in predominantly rural parishes. Vizzard spent most of the years between 1955 and 1968 as the sole NCRLC representative in Washington. From June, 1958 to June, 1960 he was based in Des Moines, Iowa, helping the NCRLC battle a financial crisis. In recognition of his efforts in the behalf of rural people, Pope Paul VI awarded Vizzard the Benemerenti medal in 1968, when poor health forced him to resign his position with the NCRLC. Some of the legislative highlights of Vizzard's career as NCRLC lobbyist include the passage of the Migrant Medical Help Law in 1962, the Farm Labor Contractor Registration Act in 1963, and the repeal of Public Law 78 (the bracero bill) in 1964. Vizzard testified more than one hundred times before congressional committees. In 1964, he co-chaired the National Conference on Poverty in the Southwest with Walter P. Reuther of the AFL-CIO and James Patton of the National Farmers Union. In addition to his numerous organizational affiliations, Fr. Vizzard maintained a heavy speaking schedule and published many articles. After returning to California in 1968, Vizzard took up a new challenge: the directorship of the then-dormant Social Apostolate of the California Province of the Society of Jesus. Vizzard felt that his fellow Jesuits had become too complacent about the social and economic ills of modern society, and he urged them to become fighters for social justice and civil rights. During this period, her lived for a year with two other priests in a low-income section of San Jose. He also served on the national board of directors of Project Equality, a group made up of clergy dedicated to eliminating discrimination within their own ranks and using the purchasing power of churches and religious organizations to support socially responsible companies. In 1972, Vizzard accepted an invitation from Cesar Chavez to become the legislative representative of the United Farm Workers union. Chavez asked that he concentrate immediately on strengthening the 1963 Farm Labor Contractor Registration Act, which had proved difficult to enforce. Vizzard's intensive months of lobbying came to fruition with the signing of the Farm Labor Contractor Registration Act Amendments of 1974. Another notable success was the Child Labor Law Amendment of 1974, which prohibited children under twelve from working in the fields. Other major issues of concern to the UFW included the proposed extension of the National Labor Relations Act to cover farm workers, unemployment insurance for farm workers, efforts to curb the influx of undocumented workers into the United States, and support for the 160-acre limitation for farms receiving water at federally-subsidized rates. In 1974, Vizzard was appointed by Secretary of Labor Peter Brennan to the Standards Advisory Committee on Agriculture, Occupational Safety and Health Administration. Fr. Vizzard resigned his post with the UFW in 1977 and retired to Santa Clara, California.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The James L. Vizzard Papers document the activities of a Jesuit priest who spent more than thirty years lobbying, writing and speaking on behalf of migrant laborers, braceros and the rural poor in the United States. As the Washington representative for the National Catholic Rural Life Conference (and later for the United Farm Workers), Vizzard was instrumental in influencing legislation aimed at improving the lot of the largely unorganized agricultural labor force. The collection, which spans 16.5 linear feet, is comprised of correspondence, reports, newsletters, articles, minutes, agendas, legislative testimony, press releases, newsclippings, an oral history tape, and photographs. The records date from 1942 to 1983, the bulk having been generated between 1955 and 1977. The collection is arranged into eight series, the contents and arrangement of which are described below.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
- SERIES I: PERSONAL AND BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION, 1950-1983
  The first series includes thirteen appointment calendars, dating from 1955 to 1976, which give an indication of the breadth of Vizzard's activities and travels, and the names of legislators, lobbyists, and activists with whom he conferred. Other items include personal correspondence, a papal medal and scroll, resumes, tributes to Vizzard on the occasion of his farewell to Washington, D.C. dinner (1968), newsclippings, and printed programs of events in which Vizzard took part.
- SERIES II: WRITINGS OF JAMES L. VIZZARD, S.J., 1949-1977
  Series II is comprised of Vizzard's writings: articles, statements and position papers in both draft and published form, transcripts of speeches, and a substantial body of legislative testimony, dating from 1949 to 1977. Topics which figure prominently in Vizzard's articles and testimony include: migrants and migrant health, the campaign to defeat Public Law 78 (the bracero bill), federal water reclamation and irrigation laws, the Delano Grape Strike, and Cesar Chavez's struggle to organize farm laborers.
- SERIES III: NATIONAL CATHOLIC RURAL LIFE CONFERENCE, 1942-1968
  The third series is lengthy, as it contains Vizzard's records pertaining to his thirteen-year stint as lobbyist for the National Catholic Rural Life Conference. The NCRLC, founded in 1942 and based in Des Moines, Iowa, had several fundamental goals: the preservation of the family-owned farm, the promotion of social justice and economic security for those who worked on the land, and the fostering of increased appreciation of the value of agricultural life in general. Vizzard helped to create the position of Washington representative for himself and proved to be a tenacious and highly-visible spokesman for change in agricultural policy. The bulk of the NCRLC series consists of correspondence between Vizzard and fellow-members, staff and board members. Outdoing letters are arranged chronologically; in-coming correspondence is alphabetical by the name of the correspondent. There is a separate sub-series containing correspondence with NCRLC staff and officers, among them NCRLC founder, Monsignor Luigi G. Ligutti. Additional NCRLC include annual reports, minutes, agendas, convention programs, and Vizzard's Washington office activity and financial reports. (The subject files maintained by Vizzard during his NCRLC years may be found in Series VI.) Vizzard's role as a lobbyist included participation in a multiplicity of activities aimed at serving the NCRLC membership and influencing agricultural legislation. He was an indefatigable writer of letters and articles, including many for Catholic Rural Life, the NCRLC monthly magazine, and for non-religious publications as well. He researched issues and made certain that his friends in Congress, especially Senators Harrison Williams of New Jersey and George Aiken of Vermont, were made aware of his findings. Their successful campaigns led to the passage of the Migrant Medical Help Law in 1962 (Williams called this the first piece of pro-farm worker legislation since the Depression), the Farm Labor Contractor Registration Act in 1963, and the defeat of bracero legislation in 1964. Vizzard urged legislators, the NCRLC and the Catholic hierarchy alike to take a progressive, pro-labor stand on the agricultural issues of the day.
- SERIES IV: SOCIAL APOSTOLATE, CALIFORNIA PROVINCE, SOCIETY OF JESUS, 1968-1972
  Series IV contains correspondence and administrative files maintained by Vizzard during his directorship of the Social Apostolate for the California Jesuit province. Vizzard's attempts at reviving the moribund social action ministry of this province included meeting and planning with many Catholic leaders from other parts of the country. Vizzard corresponded widely, published a newsletter and wrote a report on conditions within the province, and made recommendations for Jesuit involvement. Vizzard served on the national board of project Equality, a coalition of religious groups dedicated to using their purchasing and investment power to patronize socially responsible corporations and financial institutions, and to promote equal employment opportunities for minorities.
- SERIES V: UNITED FARM WORKERS, 1972-1977
  The fifth series dated from 1972 to 1977, the years which Vizzard spent in Washington as lobbyist for the United Farm Workers. The records in this series include correspondence, reports, and newsletters received from UFW headquarters in Delano, California, subject files maintained by Vizzard in Washington, legislative files, and extensive newsclipping and press release files. Of primary concern to Vizzard was the outcome of the UFW boycott and strike activities and the subsequent press response. At the same time, he worked with Burton Fretz of the Migrant Legal Action Program, the Reverend Wayne C. Hartmire of the National Farm Workers Ministry, and Monsignor George G. Higgins of the National Catholic Welfare Conference, to protect the civil rights of migrants, children and undocumented workers. There is a small amount of correspondence to Vizzard from Cesar Chavez and other UFW leaders, including Gilbert Padilla and Jerome Cohen. The papers in this series provide and overview of the concerns of the UFW from 1972 to 1977, rather than an in-depth analysis of the union's inner workings.
- SERIES VI: SUBJECT FILES, 1953-1977
  There are nearly thirteen boxes (6.5 linear feet) of topically-arranged correspondence, reports, minutes, agendas, notes, newsletters and newsclippings in the sixth series. Some of the well-known correspondents include Henry P. Anderson (Agricultural Workers Organizing Committee), Fay Bennett (National Sharecroppers Fund), Shirley Greene (National Farmers Union), and George Meany and Walter Reuther (AFL-CIO). Vizzard was a prominent, energetic member of the Catholic Association for International Peace, 1955-1964, and the Citizens Crusade Against Poverty, 1964-1967. In 1966, Vizzard served as chairman of a coalition of over forty organizations, the National Council on Agricultural Life and Labor. There are files on number of other agricultural, Catholic, educational and economic organizations within this series. Important topics in the General Sub-series of the Subject Files include five years of correspondence between Vizzard and Salinas grower William O. Garin concerning the bracero situation in California. Vizzard received national press coverage for his role as co-chairman of the Poverty in the Southwest conference held in Tucson in 1965. Also in this sub-series is his correspondence with Secretary of Labor James Mitchell and senators and congressmen, including Senators George Aiken, Harrison Williams, Paul Douglas, Hubert Humphrey, John F. Kennedy and Wayne Morse and Representative Leonor Sullivan. At the conclusion of the alphabetically-arranged General Sub-series, there are five sub-series concerning topics which Vizzard studied in depth: the Delano Grape Strike, 1965-1967; Farm Labor Contractors Registration Act, 1964-1976; Migrants, 1953-1967; Public Law 78 (Braceros)1957-1967 and Westlands Water District/160-Acre Limitation, 1956-1977. Vizzard evinced his strong sympathy for the grape pickers in Delano and their leader, Cesar Chavez, by urging the Catholic Church and other religious leaders to speak in favor of the strike and join the picketing in the fields. The widespread publicity given to his stand angered Bishop Aloysius Willinger of the Monterey-Fresno Diocese, who wrote bitter newspaper attacks against Vizzard. Fr. Vizzard visited Delano and joined with Catholic, Protestant and Jewish leaders to form the Committee of religious Concern to support the strike. The Delano Strike papers include corresponding, newsletters, and press releases. The final four sub-series pertain to key legislative issues, including the Farm Labor Contractors Registration Act of 1963, which was designed to curb abuses by the crew leaders who supplied farm laborers to growers. When Vizzard returned to Washington in 1972, Chavez asked him to give highest priority to strengthening the act and its enforcement. Working closely with Burton Fretz of the Migrant Legal Action Program, Vizzard helped to draft the legislation and ensure the passage of amendments to the act, which were signed into law by President Gerald Ford on December 7, 1974. This sub-series contains notes, drafts and legislative materials about the original act and amendments, dating from 1964 to 1976. The exploitation of migrant workers and braceros was of great concern to Vizzard. He maintained files on each group, which include correspondence and newsclippings. Other items of note are a television script entitled "Harvest of Shame," some migrant case histories, and information on the farm worker struggle in Rio Grande City, Texas. The final sub-series is comprised of correspondence, statements, reports, and newsclippings pertaining to the Westlands Water District in California, and the federal 160-acre limitation. There is a considerable amount of correspondence with Dr. Paul S. Taylor, Vizzard's mentor and an emeritus professor of economics at the University of California at Berkeley, who had been crusading in favor of the allocation of federally-subsidized water to small farms since the 1930s. Vizzard and Taylor saw many violations of the so-called 160-acre limitation, a situation that had allowed large corporate farms to thrive at the expense of their family-owned counterparts.
- SERIES VII: ORAL HISTORY, 1980
  Series VII is an oral history tape and partial transcript of an interview conducted by Anne Loftis, author of A Long Time Coming, The Struggle to Unionize America's Farm Workers.
- SERIES VIII: PHOTOGRAPHS
  The final series is comprised of photographs of Vizzard, migrant workers (ca. 1963), and Teamster strike breakers (ca. 1973).
CONTAINER LIST
- SERIES I: PERSONAL AND BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION, 1950-1983
  - Subseries A. Appointment Calendars
    - Appointment Calendars 1955, 1957, 1958, 1959, 1960, 1961, 1963, 1967, 1968, 1971, 1972, 1973, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Subseries B. Personal Correspondence, In-Coming And Out-Going
    - Personal Correspondence, In-Coming And Out-Going 1950-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries C. Biographical Information
    - Benemerenti Medal, presented to Vizzard on Apr. 2, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Benemerenti Scroll, and note, n.d. Mar. 22, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Biographical information, 1955-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Farewell to Washington, DC dinner, Apr. 2, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Legal documents, 1961; 1966; 1968; 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Medical records, 1965-1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Newsclippings about Vizzard, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Religious records, 1955-1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Printed programs and reports (Vizzard listed as a participant), 1956-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- SERIES II: WRITINGS OF JAMES L. VIZZARD, S.J., 1949-1977
  - Subseries A. Articles, Statements And Position Papers
    - Catholic Rural Life, articles, 1956-1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Drafts of articles, statements, and position papers, 1951-1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Drafts of articles, statements, and position papers, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Drafts of articles, statements, and position papers, 1964-1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Drafts of articles, statements, and position papers (1), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Drafts of articles, statements, and position papers (2), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Journal articles, 1956-1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Journal articles, 1963-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "The Morality of Industrialized Agriculture," 1949 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper articles, 1957-1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B. Speeches And Invocations
    - Speeches And Invocations 1952-1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Speeches And Invocations 1963-1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Subseries C. Legislative Testimony
    - Legislative Testimony 1952-1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Legislative Testimony 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Legislative Testimony 1964-1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- SERIES III: NATIONAL CATHOLIC RURAL LIFE CONFERENCE, 1942-1968
  - Subseries A. Out-Going Correspondence
    - Out-Going Correspondence Mar.-Dec., 1955 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Jan.-June, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Out-Going Correspondence July-Dec., 1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Jan.-June, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Out-Going Correspondence July-Dec., 1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Jan.-Mar., 1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Apr.-May, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Out-Going Correspondence June-July, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Aug.-Dec., 1958 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Jan., 1959-Dec., 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Jan.-Apr., 1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Out-Going Correspondence May-July, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Sept.-Oct., 1961 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Nov.-Dec., 1961 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Jan.-Feb., 1962 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Mar.-Apr., 1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Out-Going Correspondence May-Aug., 1962 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Sept.-Dec., 1962 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Jan.-Apr., 1963 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Out-Going Correspondence May-Aug., 1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Sept.-Dec., 1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Jan.-Apr., 1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Out-Going Correspondence May-Aug., 1964 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Sept.-Dec., 1965 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Jan.-June, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Out-Going Correspondence July-Dec., 1965 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Jan.-Mar., 1966 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Apr.-May, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Out-Going Correspondence June-Dec., 1966 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Out-Going Correspondence Jan.-Apr., 1967 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Out-Going Correspondence May-Dec., 1967 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B. In-Coming Correspondence
    - Academy-Aziere (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Baer-Bookbinder (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Boyer-Byrne (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Cahalan-Christensen (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Citizens-Contant (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Cook-Cyliakus (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Daley-Dzuik (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Eklund-Extension (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Faith-Fuqua (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Galarza-Guilderson (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Hadwiger-Helfrich (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Herderson-Hylden (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Independent-July (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Kane-Krzycki (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Lachana-Lyman (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - M-Mamer (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Manhattanville-Mayer (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Medeiros-Murray (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Naglee-Nunley (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - O'Brien-Purcell (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Quinn, Frances-Quinn, William (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Radtke-Rickert (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Rieck-Russell (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Saint-Schulte (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Scott-Sims (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Skillin-Szold (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Tablet-Twomey (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Umbrian-Voorhis (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Wagner-Wright (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Xerox-Zimmers (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Subseries C. Correspondence With Ncrlc Staff And Officers
    - Dineen, Fr. Michael P., 1955-1956 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Dineen, Fr. Michael P, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Dineen, Fr. Michael P, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Freking, Bshp.. Frederick W., 1964-1967 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Jennings, Dana, 1958-1965 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Ligutti, Msgr. Luigi G., 1954-1955 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Ligutti, Msgr. Luigi G., 1956 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Ligutti, Msgr. Luigi G., 1957 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Ligutti, Msgr. Luigi G., 1958 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Ligutti, Msgr. Luigi G., 1959-1961 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Ligutti, Msgr. Luigi G., 1962., 1964 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Ligutti, Msgr. Luigi G., 1965-1967 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Marling, Bshp. Joseph M., 1961-1962 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Meisner, Joseph, 1957-1968 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - O'Rourke, Msgr. Edward W., 1955-1960 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - O'Rourke, Msgr. Edward W., 1961 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - O'Rourke, Msgr. Edward W., 1962 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - O'Rourke, Msgr. Edward W., 1963 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - O'Rourke, Msgr. Edward W., 1964 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - O'Rourke, Msgr. Edward W., 1965-1967 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Pursley, Bshp. Leo A., 1958-1963; 1967 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Ramacher, Fr. Edward T., 1958 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Weber, Msgr. John George, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Weber, Msgr. John George, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Weber, Msgr. John George, 1963-1968 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Woznicki, Bshp. Steven S., 1957-1964 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Inter-office Memoranda, 1957-1961 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Subseries D. Administrative Files
    - Annual Convention, Oct. 22-26, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Annual Convention, Oct. 16-22, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Annual Convention, Oct. 7-11, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 3)